So, we've learned how to make a
decision, but sometimes the decision has
multiple steps within it, multiple
decisions that you want to make. So,
when you want to stack decisions, you
can actually just stack the if
statements inside of each other. So, um
I'm going to clear this and we're going
to do a different example. Um we're
going to do the example of a calculator.
So, we're going to um prompt the user to
ask them if they want to make a
calculation. So, we're going to say, let
make calculation equal prompt.
Do you want to make
a calculation?
And then um we can make use an if
statement. So we'll say if
um make calculation
is yes
then we want to do something otherwise
we want to alert goodbye.
Well that's great. Um
but once we have figured out that they
want to make a calculation we want to
ask them what kind of calculation they
want to make. So um let's ask them. So
we'll say let um operation equal prompt.
What operation would you like to use?
And then it we'll put add, subtract,
multiply,
divide
just to give the user some um options.
I'm going to close this side panel so
you can see all of my code. So,
we're going to ask them if they want to
make a calculation. If they said yes,
then we want to ask them what kind of
operation they'd like to use. Otherwise,
we'd just like to tell them goodbye.
Now that we are in know that they want
to make a calculation. Now, we need to
figure out if they said add, subtract,
multiply or divide. So, that's another
decision-making process. So, let's
create another if statement. So we'll
say if
operation
is add
then we're going to say oh actually we
should prompt them for two numbers. So
we're going to ask if they want to make
a calculation. If they do then we're
going to ask them for two numbers. So
we'll say let num one equal prompt. What
is your number? What is
number one?
And then we'll get number two. Let num
two equal prompt. What is number two?
So we're going to prompt them for two
numbers. We're going to ask them what
kind of operation they'd like to do. If
they say add, then we want to alert.
And I'm going to use those characters.
The
sum of
num one and
num two
is
num one plus num two. And I realized um
num one and num two right now they are
coming back from a prompt as a string.
So we probably want to make them into a
number. So let's do that. So we'll say
parse float just in case they enter um
something with a decimal place and we'll
parse float on this one as well.
So we're saying ask for number one turn
it into a float. Ask for number two turn
it into a float. ask them what operation
they'd like to perform. If they said
add, then give them the sum. Um, and
then I'm going to say else if operation
is subtract
then alert
the result is
and then we'll concatenate on. num one
minus num two
and you could keep going and you could
do multiply and divide for the sake of
time. I am just going to stop there. So
what we've done is we've nested a
decision in the decision. So we said if
they said yes then we want to um do some
processing. Part of that processing is
we want to decide if we want to add or
subtract. If they said no then we just
want to say goodbye. So we'll save this
and
we'll visit our web page and it says do
you want to make a calculation? We'll
say yes. And then it says what is number
one? One. What is number two? One. Do
you want to add, subtract, multiply or
divide? If I say add, then I get the sum
of one and one is two. If I reload the
page, it says, do you want to make a
calculation? I can say yes. Um, what is
number one? Five. What is number two?
Two. Do you want to add, subtract,
multiply, or divide? We can say subtract
and it says the result is three. So 5 -
2 is 3. And if we reload, do you want to
make a calculation? And if we type
anything but yes, then we get goodbye.
So in that way we were able to um make a
decision and within our decision we were
able to make a different decision and
that is how nesting if statements works.